在我们继续进行函数建模之前，让我们再做一件事。
Let's do one more thing before we move on from function modelling.
我们这里有一个减速器。
We have here a reducer.
我定义了 contramap，在它进入之前我们用 f 击中 x。
And I defined contramap where we hit the x with the f before it goes in.
我们有一个连接。
And we have a concat.
这个有点意思
This one's kinda interesting.
这说，好吧，我有另一个减速器，对，我有我的减速器。
This says, well, I have another reducer, right, and I have my reducer.
我要做的是运行我的累加器 X 和
And what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna run my accumulator an X and
换个新的蓄能器吧？
get a new accumulator, right?
这就是它返回给我的东西，它可以是下一个减速器的累加器。
That's what this returns me, which can be the accumulator of the next reducer.
所以通过运行我的减速器，使用相同的累加器，
So by running my reducer, with that same accumulator in value,
我得到一个新的累加器，它被传递给下一个。
I get a new accumulator which gets passed to the next one.
所以它更像是一个组合。
So it is much more like a composition.
如果我们深入一点，让我先展示一下，
And if we dig in a little bit deeper, let me first show how this,
我想在这里设置一下。
I wanna set this up for a second here.
所以我有点像 Redux c 风格的应用程序。
So I'm kind of modeling a little like Redux c style app.
你不需要知道 Redux 是什么，但它是一个常见的架构，并且
You don't need to know what Redux is, but it is a common architecture, and
所以我只想稍微浏览一下。
so I just wanna like walk through this for a second.
所以我们有一个登录减速器，所以我们的累加器状态，我们的值有效载荷。
So we have a login reducer, so our accumulator state, our values payload.
我们是说，如果我们有电子邮件，我们会尝试登录。
And we're saying, if we have an email, we'll try to login.
我将检查 admin 和 123 的凭据并说，登录是否正确。
I'll check the credentials for admin and 123 and said, logged in is true or not.
否则我们只会返回状态，因为他们总是必须返回一个累加器。
Otherwise we'll just return state back cuz they always have to return an accumulator.
如果您有偏好，则设置偏好，
Set preferences will just if you've got preferences,
我们实际上会设置它们，否则返回状态。
we'll actually set them otherwise return state.
好的，很酷，所以我们有两个减速器。
Okay, cool, so we have two reducers.
现在我们要做的是
Now we're gonna do,
我是不是要把它们放在 reducer 类型的官方函数建模 reducer 中。
is I'm gonna throw them in reducer kind of official function modelling reducers.
所以我可以把它们结合起来。
So I can combine them.
然后，我将运行 login: false、preferences 和
And then, I'm gonna run the loggedIn: false, preferences, and
你有我的用户名和密码是正确的。
you've got my username and password are correct.
如果我运行它，只需保存并运行它。
If I run that, just save this and run it.
我真的登录了，它正在准备中，太好了。
I get logged in true, and it's at the preps, great.
如果我把名字弄乱了，就不会登录，而假的，
If I mess up the name, doesn't get logged in, while false,
很酷，所以这是这里的首选项。
cool, so it's the prefs over here.
好了，大家开心就好。
All right, everybody's happy.
现在，我可以在这里玩转这些类型。
Now, I can play around with the types here.
这有点深入到我们开始的原因
And this is kinda getting down to the meat of why we're starting
建模函数是，这里我们有一个累加器和
to model functions is, here we have an accumulator and
一个 a 并且我们返回一个累加器，对吗？
an a and we return an accumulator, right?
我们知道，如果我们在这里翻转类型，那是相同的功能，对吧？
And we know that if we flip the types here, that's the same function, right?
如果我预先拥有这两个，我可以将它们翻转过来，功能相同。
If I have both of these up front, I could just flip them around, same function.
如果我一次给它一个会怎样？
What happens if I give it one at a time?
我可以提供一个同构证明，说明我可以对一个函数进行柯里化和取消柯里化。
I can provide an isomorphism proof that says, I can curry and uncurry a function.
所以我可以轻松地一次接受一个论点。
So I can easily take one argument at a time.
现在发生了什么？
And now what's happening?
这是什么？
What it is?
那是内吗？
Is that endo?
什么是end呢？
What's endo right there?
好吧，如果我们把 A 变成end呢？
Okay, what if we turned A into endo?
好吧，它变得有趣了。
Okay, it's getting interesting.
如果，这只是一个函数，对吗？
And what if, and this is just a function, right?
我想结合这些功能。
I want to combine these functions.
所以我会把它放到一个函数中。
So I'll put that into a function.
现在代替减速器，我只是浏览了我玩过的类型
Now instead of a reducer, I just walked through the types I played around with
等价的类型，我已经结束了这种类型。
equivalent types, and I've ended up at this type.
那是一种乐趣。
That's kind of fun.
[笑] 让我们看看，我知道它是等价的。
[LAUGH] Let's see, and I know it's equivalent.
这是一个更深入的主题，我不会深入探讨。
This is a deeper subject that I'm not gonna go too deep into.
但是看着玩弄参数类型，移动它们，携带，
But looking at playing around with argument types, moving them around, carry,
不携带，打包东西，有点引导你进入其中的一些解决方案。
uncarrying, packaging things up, kind of leads you into some of these solutions.
你可以说我有自己的功能，我会建模，它会很棒。
Where you can say I have my own function, I'm gonna model it, it's gonna be great.
你写了所有这些代码，你就像，等等，
And you write all this code and you're like, wait,
那只是等价于其他类型。
that's just equivalent to this other type.
[笑] 但我只是玩弄了一些争论。
[LAUGH] But I just played around with the arguments a little bit.
所以很多这几乎总是为了
So a lot of this is almost always kind of done for
你如果你调查类型。
you if you kind of investigate the types.
但是让我们继续，让我们继续这个，我们已经有了一个函数并且
But let's go ahead, let's go right this, we already have a function and
内定义。
endo defined.
所以，而不是说，我有一个登录和
So instead of saying, I have a login and
我要把它和这件事联系起来。
I'm gonna concat that with this thing.
我要在这里做这个，我们会说登录功能。
I'm gonna do this right here, we'll say of a function of login.
我们可以使用 set prefs 函数来连接它。
We can concat that with a function of set prefs.
我们刚刚说，我们要一个一个地翻转这些，对吗？
And we just said, we're gonna flip these around take one at a time, right?
所以让我们做那个状态，有效载荷和状态。
So let's do that state, payload and state.
现在当然，我们想把它放到endo中。
Now of course, we wanna put this into endo.
正如我们所说，这样做。
And do that, as we said.
实际上，这是一种奇怪的 API。
And actually, this is kind of a weird API.
为什么不，我只是把它映射到一个内端，或者抱歉，
Why don't, I just map this an endo, or sorry,
您可以将功能映射到endo，这可以工作。
you can map the function into endo, that could work.
在我尝试之前，让我看看我是否可以先让它工作。
Let me see if I can get this to work first before I try that.
[笑] 但这个想法是我可以把它推到这里或者
[LAUGH] But the the idea is I can kind of push this out over here or
将它嵌入我的函数定义本身。
embed it in my function definition itself.
如果我愿意，我可以在此处放置一个函数。
I could have put a function right here if I wanted to.
这些是关于我的 API 的决定，我是否想尝试提升
These are decisions about my API, whether I wanna try to lift
所有这些事情都变成了正确的类型，有点在背景中或
all these things into the right type, kind of in the background or
如果我想公开，那就是你如何制作这些功能。
if I wanna expose, that's how you make these functions.
好的，那么现在我该如何处理？
Okay, so now how do I work with this?
好吧，现在状态并没有立即赋予它，而有效载荷却可以。
Well, now state doesn't get given to it right off the bat, and a payload does.
这会返回给我一个 End，然后我将使用 state 运行它。
And that returns me an endo and then I'll run that with state.
所以我们把这两个分开了，如果我弄错了密码，它仍然有效。
So we've separated these two, and still works, if I get the password wrong.
注销假，我。
Logged out false, me.
让我们看看我能不能把这个拉下来，放到这里的内窥镜里。
Let's see if I can pull this one off and put it into an endo here.
我不想花太多时间在这上面。
I don't wanna spend too much time on this.
所以我只是想告诉你，这是非常有趣的东西。
So I just wanted to kinda show you, this is pretty interesting stuff.
那么，这是工作吗？
So, is this work?
是的，它有效，您更改注销的 false。
Yeah, it works, you change the logged out false.
很酷，所以在我的减速器组合功能中，
Cool, so in my reducer combination function,
我实际上已经映射了函数的输出并且
I have actually mapped over the output of the function and
把它放在一个内，现在我的函数定义 API 和以前一样。
put it in an endo, and now my function definition API's the same as it was.
但我能够改变它的工作方式。
But I was able to change how this works.
另一件非常有趣的事情是，如果我在这里不需要状态，
Another thing that's really interesting is if I don't need state here,
我们将在当天晚些时候看到这一点，但我们可以考虑到这一点。
we'll see this later on the day, but we can factor this out.
真的，真的在我们解决我们可以解决的功能时玩弄类型
And really, really play around with the types as we solve the functions we can
有点像神奇地凭空出现新的论点。
kind of like magically appear new arguments out of nowhere.
所以我们也可以使用它。
So we can use that as well.
建模函数有很多很多结果，很多可能性。
Modeling functions has many, many outcomes, many possibilities.
然后有一堆等效的方法来建模函数。
Then there's a bunch of equivalent ways to model a function.
所以通过玩弄参数类型。
So by playing around with argument types.
我们可以发现对相同功能进行建模的等效方法。
We can discover equivalent ways to model the same function.
所以这些函数等价，函数建模等价 [笑] 我不
So these function equivalences, function modeling equivalences [LAUGH] I don't
知道，我认为这很酷。
know, and I think that's pretty cool.
我认为这很酷的原因之一是，当我们这样做时
One of the reasons I think that's pretty cool is that, when we did
我们有这些减速器，我们可以做像 contramap 之类的东西。
the reducer we had these, we can do stuff like contramap and everything.
当我们开始移动这些类型并改变事物时，
And when we're starting to move these types around and change things,
就像也许函数没有 contramap 而我想要那样
like maybe function doesn't have contramap and I want that so
我可以以不同的方式对其进行建模以获得它等等。
I can model it at a different way to get that and so on.
从这里回来有点难减少很容易种
It's kinda hard to get from here back to reduce was easy to kind
按照这个到那里，有点难走另一条路。
of follow this to there, a little bit harder to go the other way.